Elena Chechik

Email: elena.chechik@uni-flensburg.de elenachechik@gmail.com

Web: https://hellche.github.io

SUMMARY

I am a researcher and PhD student specializing in education science and science of sciences, with a background in economics and econometrics. My research involves studying people and their groups to estimate inequalities and develop actionable policies. **SKILLS:** Statistics, data collection, preprocessing, exploratory and statistical data analysis, textual analysis, data visualization (R, Python).

ACADEMIC AND RESEARCH POSITIONS

| Researcher & PhD student, Department of Methodology | Sep. $2023 - present$ |
|---|--------------------------|
| Europa-Universität Flensburg | $Flensburg, \ Germany$ |
| • Project: Admission Restrictions and Inequality in Higher Education. | |
| Researcher, Center for Institutional Analysis of Science & Education | Jan. 2020 - Sep. 2023 |
| European University at St.Petersburg | $St.Petersburg,\ Russia$ |
| External Researcher, Gender Wage Gap Decomposition Project | Jan. $2020 - Nov. 2021$ |
| Center for Advanced Governance | $Moscow,\ Russia$ |
| Assistant Lecturer / Teaching Assistant, Department of Economics | Oct. 2014 – Dec. 2019 |
| Samara State Technical University | Samara, Russia |
| • Courses: Economics, Econometrics. | |

RESEARCH PROJECTS

Analysis of gender gaps in academic disciplines

Based on PhD and DS dissertations data

- ISSI 2023. "Gender Disparities in Academic Disciplines: An Attempt to Fill in the Blind Spots of Bibliometrics." Chechik E. [Link: github.com/hellche/issi2023]
- Chechik E. (2023) "Gender Disparities in Research Fields in Russia: Dissertation Authors and Their Mentors." [Scientometrics, major revision]

Grant policy analysis

A study of the two largest Russian grant foundations

- Exploratory data analysis, statistical analysis for:
 - Guba K., Zheleznov A., **Chechik E.** (2023) "Evaluating grant proposals: lessons from using metrics as screening device." *Journal of Data and Information Science* [DOI: doi.org/10.2478/jdis-2023-0010]
- STI 2023. "Uncovering Barriers for Women in Russian Grant Funding: Rejected and Supported Grant Applications." Chechik E. [Link: github.com/hellche/grant_applications]

Exploring the Russian academic community

Survey of about 15,000 academic staff from five fields: sociology, economics, political science, history, law (2021-2022)

- Survey and database development, data preprocessing for:
 - Sokolov M., **Chechik E.** (2022) "Academic reputations of Russian economists and their scientometric assessments." *Voprosy ekonomiki* (In Russ.) [DOI: doi.org/10.32609/0042-8736-2022-11-117-135]

English-language publications about Russia over the past 30 years

Scientific knowledge about Russia in the fields of Social Sciences and Humanities (WoS, 1990–2020)

- Data preprocessing, exploratory data analysis for:
 - Project webpage: russiaresearch.org/project-overview/
 - GitHub repo: github.com/hellche/russian_studies/

Parenthood in academia

A Study of parenthood for female and male academic economists (survey, 2021-2022)

- Chechik E. (2023) "Parenthood and Gender in Russian Academia" Voprosy obrazovaniya, (In Russ.) [DOI: doi.org/10.17323/vo-2023-16337]
- STI 2023. "Gender, Parenthood, and Academic Performance: Work-life and Work-work Balance in Russian Academia" Chechik E. Online supplementary materials [Link: hellche.github.io/parenthood_HEI/]

Gender wage gap estimation

Analysis of the gender wage gap in 2010-2020 in Russia on two datasets

- Estimation of adjusted and unadjusted gender wage gap on the data of the Russian statistical agency and Russia Longitudinal Monitoring Survey
- Gap decomposition on an explained and unexplained (Oaxaca-Blinder method)

SCHOLARSHIPS & SUMMER SCHOOLS

RESPECT Doctoral Fellowship

Sep. 2023 – present

Georgia Institute of Technology, US

• Cassidy R. Sugimoto & Thema Monroe-White NSF-funded grant on intersectional inequalities in science.

Science of Science Summer School (S4)

Aug. 2022

SOS+CD Lab and School of Information Studies, Syracuse University, US

virtual event

• Team project: Network analysis on academic mentoring data and developed a recommendation system.

Experimental Economics Summer School

Aug. 2019

Laboratory of Experimental and Behavioural Economics, Higher School of Economics

St. Petersburg, Russia

• Team project: The Effect of Priming on Cheating in the Long-Run.

Fulbright Scholarship FFDP 2018-19

Aug. 2018 - Jan. 2019

University of Massachusetts, Department of Economics

Boston, US

• The internship in feminist economics with Prof. Julie Nelson.

EDUCATION

Higher School of Economics

Jul. 2017 – Aug. 2018

Applied Econometrics Certificate

Moscow, Russia

• Microeconometrics, Macroeconometrics, Spatial Econometrics

Samara State Technical University

Sep. 2006 – Jul. 2011

Specialist Degree in Economics (diploma with distinction)

Samara, Russia

• Business Economics, Macroeconomics, Forecasting, Banking, Stock Market

Conferences

STI 2023. Sept. 26-29 Leiden, Netherlands [conference paper; poster session]

ISSI 2023. July 2-5, Bloomington (IN), US [poster session]

ICSSI 2023. June 26-29, Evanston (IL), US [poster session]

STI 2022. Sept. 7-9 Granada, Spain [conference proceedings: zenodo.org/record/6956906

ISSI 2021. Jul. 12-15, Leuven, Belgium (virtual event) [conference proceedings:

issi-society.org/publications/issi-conference-proceedings/proceedings-of-issi-2021

SKILLS

Tools: R, Python, Stata, I₄TEX, GitHub

Languages: English (advanced), German (beginner), Russian (native)